I think so, yeah.
Hi.
Welcome back, I should say, really, isn't it?
This was presumably in your day, there wasn't a petitions committee.
We've only been going with a specialist committee we're now dealing with.
Now, not sure if you know everyone here. Greg O'Connor, I'm obviously the chair.
Yes. Hello again.
On my right here and-
Kira.
Thank you.
Nice to see you.
All right. Well-
Thank you
... 10 minutes, but I would like to leave some time for questions as well, so
appreciate you coming.
So I just wanted to start off by saying thank you very much for the opportunity.
It's such an extremely important issue, as you pretty well
know. And I have with me Tufasina, who's one of
my committee members for Pacific Justice.
So how did you want to play this? Did you want to ask your questions first or for
us to-
Well, probably just give us a summary of a
context and we'll go from questions there.
This way, we obviously take your very good submissions
read, but-
Okay. So we'll take it that the submission's read, it's mostly everything on.
But I think I should just cover a few things that have been happening, which is of
quite concern. First of all,
3.2 billion people have access to New Zealand,
direct or via Australia.
The Pacific people from the day started arriving here in the mid-'40s,
have been treated as second-class citizens all the way until today.
There's less than 16 million of us,
and we have to apply for a visa to get here.
Mid '24,
the Samoan immigration, New Zealand immigration in Samoa was open for one
hour per day.
One hour
to service 200,000 people.
Imagine this. You get a message that someone has to come for a funeral.
How do you get serviced?
Mm.
Recently in May,
there was a case of a
family, one of Samoa's prominent families, had a death there.
11 days in advance, they sent the death certificate and
asked for a visa to be able to come.
Five days out, they called me, they said that they've nothing.
Nothing.
So I went to Cameron, who as you know, worked for me once and became associate
minister, and Cameron did everything he could to see what we can resolve here.
First answer was, "We've only got one application."
The other one wasn't here.
The funeral was on the 26th.
On the 25th,
they issued a visa for one to come.
On the 26th, the other one was too late.
This is how we are continuously treated,
and this can't carry on.
The point is that
why
does New Zealand immigration continue
to treat the people of the Pacific this way?
I've just come back from Egypt
and Turkey.
In Egypt, arrive with a passport, you pay $30, and
you get an immediate visa stamped in your passport. Everybody.
No questions asked. Turkey, 57 million
visitors a year.
All they get is a passport stamp without even question.
Yeah.
And here,
New Zealand's neighbors.
This is our second home for the people of the Pacific.
We can't get here for funerals. We can't get here for anything.
And I'm going to tell you this much.
I wrote to the minister,
and the Prime Minister, and the Deputy Prime Minister, and the
associate ministers. I haven't had one response.
Yeah.
Nothing. Not a thing from them.
And I have said,
"Put your
feet in these shoes."
You've just had a message.
Your mother's died,
your father's died, or your brother or sister's died.
Yeah.
Or your child has died, and you can't go to the funeral.
Wear those shoes and understand the situation that we're in.
So I've raised everything already pretty clearly,
and all I ask is that the people of
the Pacific be treated equally as anybody
else.
I don't want you to come back say, "Yes, we will do this, but these are the things
we want the Pacific people to do different from somebody else."
Because that would be totally unfair
in any way, whichever way you look at it.
So I'm honored and pleased that we're meeting today.
I know you're all of the same mind that fairness resides.
Yeah.
Fairness resides.
And we haven't been treated fairly in any way at all.
We can't be for funerals. We can't come for graduations.
We can't come when a terminal ill member of the family.
We can't come.
Why do we have to apply? Why do we have to pay all the money to come?
Why do we have to be scrutinized in everything they do?
And yet,
3.2 billion people can arrive in this country directly or via
Australia.
Yeah.
Some we went to war with.
Some have done absolutely nothing for us.
Yeah.
And we came here in the '40s, and we contributed to this country-
Yeah
... and built this country.
Sorry.
So can you, just because I'm watching the time tick down, I know
all of this really, really well. There's just so many questions I have.
Yeah.
I'm just scared we're going to run out of such valuable time.
Okay, I'll zip. You ask the questions.
Australia was-- go back to Australia
Very quickly, Talofa lava. And
we were pretty successful with the last request, so let's see how it can
go with this.
Presumably, you're happy that the
NZETA would still have to be filled out,
even if there's a visa waiver.
Whatever has to be done. We can meet all those requirements on the proviso we're
treated equally and fairly with justice as for everybody else.
Because all of those countries, the visa waiver countries, you still have to fill
in that. So-
I just want to add something, but Americans have entrance
visa on arrival.
They are number three on your overstay list.
And ahead of things-
Sorry.
Sorry. Just wanted one more.
Thank you.
New Zealand's overstays at this point of time, I believe, is 20,000.
20% are Pacific. That equates to
0.78% of New Zealand's population.
Is that an issue?
Yeah, it is, because it's proportional and that's-- So can we jump to that and
other issue?
Yes.
Cool. Awesome. This is it. I
hear all of that, but it's not completely irrational, right?
Because I've had so many conversations now with the immigration
minister and with their senior advisors, that
it is 100% to do with the concern that in the
absence of having that visa, we would end up with a flood of
overstayers based on current and historic behavior.
So can we just jump straight to talking about that?
Yep.
So what's--
It's the chicken and the egg, right?
What you're saying, from the conversations that we've had, is
that you're confident that that overstaying wave
that New Zealand fears won't happen.
And what New Zealand's saying is,
on what basis can you give New Zealand that confidence,
given the current situation with, proportionately, Pacific overstaying
is so much higher than for many other country.
So,
is it that we extend, first of all, the sense of going, "Okay, we
trust you. Absolutely it's going to change." Or is there something that
you guys can do that then gives the confidence?
It's who blinks first.
Well, put it this way.
Yeah.
I'm going to tell you right now, if we succeed, you will get a flood.
You will get a flood.
Of people coming, but not overstaying, eh?
Not overstaying. You'll get a flood of people coming, right?
Yeah.
Anywhere in the world would be the same.
When you open a floodgate, you get a flood, irrespective of its water or settle.
100%. But how can you give the confidence to New Zealand that the overstaying, that
that flood's not going to be a permanent flood and you're going to end up with this
massive overstay?
Okay. I think I've said it in my original papers to you.
First of all,
anybody who overstays doesn't come back for 10
years.
Right.
That's a tough one, but I mean it. One isn't going to spoil it for everybody else.
But overstaying has been the creation of New Zealand Immigration
themselves. Why?
If you make it difficult for anybody to come-
Correct. Which is what I'm saying is, it's chicken and egg, right?
Yeah. And they're going to hang in the stock because there's no guarantee they can
come back tomorrow.
100%. Understand.
So this is what I'm saying.
Yeah.
Follow this.
Anybody overstays, bingo. 10 year, out of here, not coming back.
Okay.
Secondly, New Zealand Immigration have to accept, after three months, if
they leave on time, they can come back if they stay with no questions asked or
anything else, and get another visa.
The same way as any other country.
As any other country.
What are the limitations of the fact?
You can't do that indefinitely, but yep, absolutely.
You do that, you will eliminate-
Right
... overstaying. Right?
And that's where the trouble right lies.
And the other thing, what is the real creation of overstay? Let me tell you this.
I think it's 34 years now, we come out and said we have
immigration consultants only registered by New Zealand Immigration.
Right.
They never carried that out.
Okay.
They never carried that out. They allowed third parties to go and make
applications for people and charge them money. Now, follow the scenario.
I've paid somebody money and
believe they're going to fix my papers.
Yeah.
I'm sitting at home waiting. I've done my bit.
Next thing, I'm an overstayer.
Yeah.
I'm going to be deported.
And I've done everything. So who is to blame for this?
Is it the person? Is it a government failing in their own rules?
The gov-
Can you also speak to the Samoan government's nervousness
about this making the change that you guys are asking for?
No, the Samoan government's not nervous about this part.
They're not nervous when they understand we are talking about
visitors visa only, not immigration in any way.
Yeah. No, it was the former prime minister.
She's obviously no longer.
Okay. No.
But she
did expressively
make her concerns known around this change.
That's because she wouldn't listen and talk to me.
Right.
To understand there's a difference between immigration-
Yeah
... and there's a difference for a visitor's visa.
Yeah. So her concern was the fact that there would be this wave that would come
from the islands and would overstay in New Zealand.
No. She thought and understood this to be an immigration issue. It is not.
That's where the problem lies. See, if you go back-
Right
... the Samoan citizenship case.
Privy Council decision was clear. Muldoon threw it out.
For 42 years, the Samoan people waited.
27 years of my life, right?
When 80% of the people have died, they decide to do something, but it's not 100%.
Yeah.
Right? Now, why did I not fight for the heirs'
rights? Because the Privy Council decision was clear.
The heirs had the same rights.
I didn't fight for that for one reason, mass migration.
Mm.
Right.
And I ruled that out and never argued.
But what I do argue
is that the Privy Council decision, the wife of somebody who fitted that
had the same rights, and you're not accepting that, and I intend to challenge that
too.
No. Good discussion. I think it forms the basis of
the The issue-
Can I-
Yes, Mr. Bailey. I would be-
So we've got the-
I'm well aware that you were patiently waiting
Oh.
Very patient, says
Arthur.
From the 1st of June 2026, the temporary reduction of
the visitor visa fees takes
effect.
Also, there was that new
temporary visa waiver pathway put in last year.
Have they helped at all or not?
My question to that is why? Why do we have to be regulated
by that when 3.2 billion people have access without that?
Because of the overstaying fear.
Just that. So let's just pick up on Greg's point then.
You're saying that
you would like to see immigration specialists
basically nominated by Immigration New Zealand to deal just with the
Pacific Islands immigrants coming in.
If you went down that route, do you think that they would guarantee that no one was
an overstayer?
No.
As I said to you, the rules I've set on this thing are tough.
Mm-hmm.
And that's enough to put anybody else.
If you made it simple for people to come and go, this won't happen.
But I warned you, there will be a flood. It will happen.
Any country in the world, it will happen.
When you've been held up for so long and going through all the problems that
you've had to go through, what do you think is going to happen?
Of course you will. Any country in the world will do the same thing.
Now that you've got eight hours of processing at Immigration New Zealand, because
you've credited the one hour, but that's obviously changed.
Have we seen a massive increase in the last year or so? No.
Why did these people couldn't get the funeral?
They waited for 11 days after filing the death certificate.
They don't give a damn. I'm telling you.
Wasn't necessary the one-hour restriction.
It was still the delay it takes Immigration New Zealand processing.
The attitude to processing doesn't exist.
They don't care.
Oh, it's not. That's the main to a lot of them, actually.
All right. So can we-
There is a particular way.
Greg just--
Well, okay. We'll have to keep moving, but just finally to address, and Greg
went straight to the-- Greg brought his elephant with him and
put it on the table around the overstaying issue, which is
always underlying. And we've heard your response to that.
If the immigration officials were here, the ones that are really driving
this policy,
what would they say now?
Trudy, they're not going to say. I've given the answer.
My answers are clear.
But you've spoken to them, and they will still say this is driven by a
fear of overstay.
I've never spoken to them. That's what keeps on thrown back in our faces
continuously is overstaying, overstaying, overstaying,
historically. Always has been.
Well, it's not just historically, it's currently as well. So the current numbers.
Yeah, but go and have a look. The answers are there that my sister
did
on the dawn raids,
and here is a report.
For all the effort and things they did, there was a very small number of people
affected by that. Right? And then there's a number of people who were
deported and should not have been deported.
With all due respect, we're not raising this issue for fun.
We've looked and identified why we are treated this way, come up with
solutions, and part of that solution was this.
The passport needs to be issued
in the name on the birth certificate
because that then becomes the controlling factor for New Zealand as well.
We are now living in modern times. Face recognition,
fingerprint recognition. You name it, it's all here, right?
So for example, if I came here on a three-month visitor visa
and I had to go and apply for a job, which I'm not supposed to.
It will pick up on my name. You could go through the system that'll sooner or after
say, "This person is only a visitor, can't be employed."
And all this can be done in the modern world we live in.
So just talk again to the passport and what's the current situation?
There is no situation. No, what I'm saying is, I'm saying if every passport, and we
tell the Samoan government the same thing, and the pursuit can only be issued
in the name as per the birth certificate.
Because that is-
So you're suggesting at the moment it can be issued in a different name?
No, because they can go and get a Matai name.
Oh, okay.
If I want to use my Matai name, I could have three or four passports, right?
Okay. Right.
I'm eliminating all that problem.
I'm saying you'll have, and also known as page.
But the governing factor is the birth certificate for everybody
worldwide.
Okay.
And these things I'm talking about,
I don't want this one-sided just for Pacific people.
Everybody has to be treated exactly the same way.
Okay.
Mm-hmm.
All right. Look, I think that's been a very good discussion, actually.
It may well be when we discuss this and when we prepare a report,
we may need to come back for some clarification on some of these points.
But no, it's been one of our more forthright discussions here,
and
thank you for
putting it on the table. So
thank you.
Can I just say that our people have been waiting anxiously what is happening here.
Mm-hmm.
Will this go to the House before it rises?
Can we ask that, and I've been here enough to see things become
suddenly over urgent overnight and get done.
Mm-hmm.
And I would like to see some action along those lines as far as this is
for the Pacific people. It's only a fair question I'm asking.
Mm-hmm.
Is it very important to us where we go from here?
Well, as I'm sure as a man who's a reasonably keen observer of the
political environment that exists at the moment, probably not.
However-
There's no such thing. I've sat on here and seen them do emergency stuff for a lot
of other stuff. If they don't think we are that important, okay, we accept that.
If you've got three parties in the coalition in full agreement, you probably would
get that. But however, that's something that we'll certainly enjoy
discussing, but probably not while we're in public.
I understand. I understand fully.
And I'll repeat, I appreciate that you put your effort in.
Okay.
We will continue to petition for things that are definitely wrong in the
Pacific.
Mm-hmm.
We don't petition for rights. We petition for justice.
That's all I ask here. Treat my people across the Pacific,
less than 16 million,
against 3.2 billion
fairly.
With justice
and respect as we do.
Thank you.
Thanks, Andrew. I'll blame you.
All right, and thanks for-
Good to see you
... making the trip down too.
And thank you both of you.
Yeah.
Thank you very much. Appreciate it.
Okay. Take care.
See you guys.